Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz, Jan. Papers, 1895-1955 (inclusive), 1918-1954 (bulk): A Finding Aid.
Papers, 1895-1955 (inclusive), 1918-1954 (bulk).
Ukrainian Research Institute Library, Harvard University
Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz, Jan.
14 boxes (5 linear feet)
The bulk of the collection is comprised of correspondence to Jan Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz from leaders of the Ukrainian government-in-exile and other Ukrainian political figures. The correspondence also consists of letters from prominent civic leaders, artists, journalists, scholars, writers, and religious figures. The remaining correspondence pertains to family, personal friends, and heraldic research. There are also subject files, writings, and personal files.
Copies of Archbishop Ratti's letters only were gift of Alexander Lotocki, 1985.
Access in by appointment only. Contact the Institute Bibliographer/Archivist.
Jan Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz (1885-1954) was born on June 24, 1885 in Chabanivka, Ushytsia county, Podilia gubernia, to Stefan and Laura Janiszewska (descendent from Polish nobility). He completed gymnasium at Zhytomyr in 1906, and then went on to obtain a doctorate in philosophy and economics at Fribourg University in Switzerland in 1909. The following year he continued his studies at the Universities of Vienna and Toulouse. In 1911-1918 he worked in the Poltava gubernial and zemstvo administrations and was general comptroller of the zemstvo Red Cross Committee. He served as an adviser to the Ukrainian National Republic missions in Vienna (June 1918 to June 1919) and Istanbul (August 1919 to March 1920) and as consul general in Istanbul (to December 1921). In Vienna on April 29, 1922 he married Oksana Lototska (her second marriage), who was born on April 14, 1897 in Kiev to Oleksander and Nymphodora Roudenko. She had also served at the Ukrainian diplomatic mission in Turkey from 1919 to 1920.
In the years 1922-1924 Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz became director of the Ministry of External Affairs for the UNR government-in-exile which was first in Poland (Tarnów from 1920-1923 and Warsaw from 1923-1939). In Paris (from 1924) he headed the International Heraldic Institute and supported the Promethean Movement; in Rome (from 1936) he worked in the Vatican Archives; and in London (from 1948) he was a leading member of the Anti-Bolshevik Bloc of Nations. His writings included numerous articles in Polish, French, Italian, German, and English on Ukrainian history, literature, and heraldry, as well as the unpublished monograph Istoriia ukrainskoi dyplomatii. Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz died in London on November 18, 1954.
Organized in four series:
I. Correspondence, 1908-1954 [Boxes 1, 2, 3]
A-G [Box 1]
H-O [Box 2]
P-Z [Box 3]
II. Subject files, 1918-1948 [Boxes 4, 5]
A-I [Box 4]
K-Z [Box 5]
III. Writings, 1923-1954 [Boxes 6, 7, 8, 9, 10]
IV. Personal files, 1895, 1906-1954 [Boxes 11, 12, 13, 14]
The collection as a whole provides insights into the immediate post-World War I period in Ukraine, especially with regard to the Ukrainian National Republic under the command of Symon Petliura and subsequently the government-in-exile. It is also a good source for studying Ukrainian political refugee life of members and employees of former Ukrainian diplomatic and economic missions of the UNR, as well as its leaders and statesmen in Paris and England.
The bulk of the collection is comprised of correspondence to Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz which is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, although some correspondence is addressed to his wife, Oksana Lototska-Tokarzewski. Most of the letters were written during their years in exile in Paris, Rome, and London. The correspondence is addressed to him from leaders of the Ukrainian government-in-exile O. Shulhyn (Choulguine), A. Livytskyi, S. Petliura, and V. Prokopovych, and includes letters from other Ukrainian political figures such as D. Doroshenko, V. Lypynskyi, M. Ieremieiv (Jeremijew), P. Shandruk (Chanedroucq), Ia. Stetsko, and M. Tyszkiewicz, as well as French political figures such as F. D'Esperey, J. Noulens, and G. Tabouis. The correspondence also consists of letters from prominent civic leaders, artists, journalists, scholars, and writers: P. Kholodnyi, V. Perebyinis, D. Chaikovskyi, V. Kedrovskyi, D. Dontsov, V. Derzhavyn, G. Genocchi, Ie. Glovinskyi, E. Insabato, R. Iendyk, F. Mazade, Iu. Rusov (Roussow), R. Smal-Stotskyi (Smal-Stocki), and I. Svientsitskyi. Important religious figures represented in the correspondence include most notably Andrii Sheptytskyi, Greek Catholic archbishop of Lviv and Greek Catholic metropolitan of Halych; Polikarp Sikorskyi, Metropolitan of the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church; T. Halushchynskyi; and Josaphat J. Jean. Family correspondence comprises letters from Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz's sister, Hélène Gromnicka, and her family, as well as Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz family members living in Lviv. Much of the rest of the correspondence pertains to personal friends and his research in heraldry. Any letters with unidentifiable signatures are filed according to the first letter of the last name, if distinguishable, and if not, are filed at the end of the series.
The series of subject files principally regard Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz's diplomatic work in Istanbul as adviser and then consul general for the UNR mission (1919-1921). These files include correspondence, reports, and statutes. Other subjects in this series relate to the Black Sea alliance, Catholic dignitaries, the famine, the Schwartzbard trial, and statutes of the Ukrainian National Republic.
Writings include both manuscripts and published articles by Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz and his wife, Oksana. His writings are on topics such as Ukrainian foreign relations, geography, history, heraldry, and politics. Most of his articles were published in ABN Correspondence, Holos molodi, France-Orient, Tryzub, Ukrainets-chas, Ukrainska dumka, and Vyzvolnyi shliakh. Oksana Lototska-Tokarzewski published articles on Ukrainian affairs as well which appeared in Conquiste, Corriere Diplomatico e Consolare, L'Idea di Roma, L'Osservatore Romano, and Vistnyk (Lviv). This series also holds Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz's research notes on various heraldries including his own.
The final series, personal files, comprises documents (i.e. birth and marriage certificates, diplomas, official governmental appointments, etc.), identifications (i.e. passports, visas, etc.), photographs (Abdulhac Hamid and Mme Ferid Bey, Louis de Bourbon, Wilhelm Habsburg-Lothringen, Simon Petliura's funeral, Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz, ABN conference, UNR government (1922)), and miscellaneous papers, pins, badges, stamps, and seals.
- I. Correspondence
  - A-G ([Box 1])
    - A 1927-1953, [Box 1, Folder 1].
      - Alabanda, Hinko (1882-1959; General), 1950-1953
      - Amet, 1935
      - Anselm, Fr., O.D.C., n.d.
      - Anti-Bolshevik of Bloc Nations, Central Committee, 1951-1954
      - Archevêché de Paris, 1933
      - Arménienne, La Délégation de la République, 1935
      - Conde de Artaza (Spanish Embassy), 1952-1953
      - Arundel de Condé, Prince d' (Exposition Coloniale Internationale de Paris), 1931-1932
      - Association des émigrés Ukrainiens à Vesines, 1934
      - Association of Ukrainian Former Combatants in Great Britain, 1952-1954
      - Association of Ukrainians in Great Britain, 1950-1954
      - Association Ukrainienne pour la Société des Nations, 1922
      - Aubac, H., 1927-1928
      - Avieténaité, M. (Ministère des Affaire Etrangères, République de Lithuanie), 1936
      - unidentified, 1928
      - unidentified, 1943
      - Anglo-Ukrainian Association, 1951-1954, [Box 1, Folder 2].
    - B 1922-1954, [Box 1, Folder 3].
      - Bagrationi di Mukhrani, Principe di Georgia, Irakly, 1943-1953
      - [Baicoy..., Ella], n.d.
      - Balinov [Balinoff], Charles, 1941-1952
      - Bammate, Haïdar, 1936-1950
      - Bandera, Stepan (1909-1959; Revolutionary, politician, and ideologue of the Ukrainian nationalist movement), 1953
      - [Barberiny], (Chambellan de Service de S.A.R. le Duc de Calabre), 1935
      - Batista i Roca, M.J.M., 1935
      - Baye, Marquis de (Archeologist), 1930
      - Beddoes, Roscoe, n.d.
      - Bellaigue, [Sal de], 1934
      - Bellew, George R. (Somerset Herald of Arts and Registrar), 1935
      - Bem de Cosban, [Wlodzimierz], 1949-1953
      - Bergonier, E., 1935
      - Bernardini-Sjoestedt, Armand, 1927-1954
      - Bertillon, Suzanne, 1946-1950
      - Bertini Frassoni, [Carlo Augusto] cte. (Collegio Araldico), 1919-1928
      - [Bette?, A. di], 1926
      - Biberovych, [Volodymyr], 1938-1954
      - Bilyi [Bilyj], I. A., 1952
      - Bilyk, Ol., 1951
      - Blois, Louis Albert comte de (Avesnes; 1880-), n.d.
      - Bohomolets, V., 1935
      - Bokitko, B., 1950
      - Bondioli, Riccardo (1897-), 1950
      - [Boning, Geneviève], 1927
      - Bramwell, Christopher (Assn. of British Members of the Sovereign Military Order of Malta), 1954
      - Britenfeld, Johanna, 1949
      - Brugada, Jose J. (Spanish Embassy), 1952
      - Buchko, Ivan (1891-1974; Ukrainian Catholic archbishop, church and civic leader; apostolic visitator of Ukrainians in Western Europe), 1951
      - Buczys, Piotr-Franciszek, 1941-19
      - Bülow, Heinrich von (1856-), 1919
      - [Burach?k, L.]
      - Buyer-Chaillot, Gaston de, 1920-1938
      - Unidentified, 1941
      - unidentified, n.d.
      - Bourbon, Prince Louis de (1865-1940), 1928-1932, [Box 1, Folder 4].
      - Bourbon, Prince Louis de (1865-1940), 1933-1939, [Box 1, Folder 5].
      - Bourbon, Prince Louis de (1865-1940), Heraldry, n.d., [Box 1, Folder 6].
      - Bourbon, Princesse Madeleine de, 1943-1950, [Box 1, Folder 7].
    - C 1918-1954, [Box 1, Folder 8].
      - [Cachellaux, H.], 1930
      - [Caleaprini-Erteny, Guido], 1942-1943
      - Cary, Margaret and Georges, 1950
      - [Cboro..., A.], 1935
      - Ceccarani, Jeruand, 1950-1954
      - Chaikovskyi, Danylo (1909-1972; editor of Ukrainets), 1952-1954
      - Chaudun, Fernand (1871-1937), 1936
      - Chaudun, Michel, 1937
      - Chebotariv, Mykola (1884-1972; Military and political figure), 1951-1954
      - Choiseul, duc de, 1935
      - Chornorai, S., 1953-1954
      - Cienski, Witold, 1954
      - Claricini, Itta de, 1950
      - Coccali, Marie, 1952-1954
      - Committee for the Aid of Refugee Ukrainian Scholars, 1946
      - Cramer, P., 1953
      - Creura, Fr. P. Th., 1946
      - Crisenoy, Carl de, 1927
      - Crisenoy, Marie Mahieu de, n.d.
      - Crivez, Alexandre de Morée, n.d.
      - Crivez, Anca de Morée and Sandu, 19
      - Csaly, E., 1918
      - unidentified last name, Emmanuel (Auxiliary Bishop of Paris), 1925
      - unidentified (Le Figaro, Paris), 1927
      - unidentified, 1927
      - unidentified, 1928
      - unidentified, ?
      - unidentified, n.d.
    - D 1920-1954, [Box 1, Folder 9].
      - Dalaise, Elza and Jean, 1921-1929
      - Davies, G. F., 1951
      - Degouy, amiral, 1928-1935
      - Derzhavyn, Volodymyr (1899-1964; Literary scholar and critic), 1954
      - Dguébouadzé, N. de, 1954
      - Diachyshyn, Fr. Petro, 1948-1949
      - Dionissius, n.d.
      - Djabadary, Suzanne, 1954
      - Dol, Henri, ?
      - Dontsov, Dmytro (1883-1973; Political journalist and theorist, editor, literary critic), 1921-1954
      - Doroshenko, Dmytro (1882-1951; Historian and historiographer and moderate conservative political figure), 1918-1950
      - Doroshenko, Nataliia (1888-1970; Stage actress and prominent figure in the theater world; wife of D. Doroshenko), 1951-1953
      - Drabat, Hryhorii (1921-1977; Journalist, civic and political activist of the OUN (Bandera faction)), 1952-1954
      - Dub-Dubowski, Ignacy (1874-1953; Bishop), 1931-1953
      - Dunin-Borkovska, Natalena (Koroleva, Natelena, 1888-1966; Writer), 1929
      - Dziuba, Fr. Volodymyr, 1948-1953
      - unidentified, 1952
    - E 1930-1950, [Box 1, Folder 10].
      - [l'Eglisy], 1932-1934
      - [Elekkhoty, Tambyi], 1930-1939
      - Enderle, Carlo, n.d.
      - [Eraville, S. d'], 1950
      - Estonian Legation, 1953
    - Franchet D'Esperey, Louis Félix Marie Francois (1856-1942; French general), 1928-1931, [Box 1, Folder 11].
    - F 1919-1954, [Box 1, Folder 12].
      - Fantenoy, 1933
      - Farkas de Kisbarnak, F., 1952-1954
      - Fediuk, Semen, 1951
      - [Fedorejowicrowy, Helena], n.d.
      - [Fedytvycky, Mykhailo] (Captain in the Army of the UNR), 1921
      - Fériol, Mufide, 1919-1920
      - Festa, Nicola, 1939
      - Follereau, Raoul, 1939-1952
      - Fuller, John, 1952-1954
      - unidentified, 1928
    - G 1922-1954, [Box 1, Folder 13].
      - Gailhard Bancel, [Hyacinthe de], 1926-1933
      - Galitsyn, Irina Princesse (1900-), 1930-1931
      - Gaucher, Georges (Ambassade de France, London), 1953
      - Genocchi, Giovanni (1860-1926; Missionary, specialist in oriental languages, and biblical scholar; apostolic visitator to Ukraine), 1922
      - Girotto, Ida and Luciano, 1946
      - Glaser, Marie, 1922
      - Glovinskyi, Ievhen (1894-1964; Economist and civic figure), 1932-1950
      - [Gr.], Seweryn, 1950-1954
      - [Gralpeck], 1948-1950
      - Greaves, John A., 1952
      - Grocholsky, Ludgard, 1940-1954
      - Gromnicka, Elisabeth von, 1942
      - Gromnicka, Ewa, 1941-1951
      - Gromnicka, Helena, 1908-1922
      - Gromnicki, Jan, 1923-1946
      - Gromnicki, Stefan, 1932-1940
      - Gromnicki, X. Tad., 1925
      - Grosjean, Georges (Academie de Marine), 1931
      - Guichery, E. de
      - Guillaume, Amédée, 1929
      - unidentified, 1922
      - unidentified, 1930
      - unidentifed, 1931
      - unidentified, 1953
      - unidentified, 1954
  - H-O ([Box 2])
    - H 1919-1953, [Box 2, Folder 14].
      - Hamit, Abdulhak (1852-1937), 1920
      - [Hadsenka, Ad.], 1930
      - Halushchynskyi, Tyt Teodosii, O.S.B.M. (1880-1952; Priest, biblical scholar, and church historian), 1949-1950
      - Haraucourt, Edmond, 1931
      - Hauschildt, John (Ukrainskyi Konsuliat, Stockholm), 1941
      - Henrys, 1937-1940
      - [Hemnrich, W.A.], 1950
      - Hérilier, P., 1920
      - Hirniak, Fr. Iustyn, 1951-1953
      - Hlaznaia, V., 1953
      - Houghton, Rev. Bryan R.S., 1936-1954
      - [Howchid, Nadjie], n.d.
      - [Husley, Lavinia], 1952
      - unidentified, 1919
      - unidentified, 1945
      - unidentified, 1950
      - unidentified, 1951-1952
      - Habsburg-Lothringen, Wilhelm (Vyshyvanyi, Vasyl; 1895-1949; Austrian army officer; colonel in the UNR war ministry), 1918-1919, 1921, 1930-1935, [Box 2, Folder 15].
      - Habsburg-Lothringen, Wilhelm, 1936-1938, [Box 2, Folder 16].
    - I 1946-1950, [Box 2, Folder 17].
      - Iakovliv, Georges (Comité de Secours aux Affamés de l'Ukraine et du Kouban), 1934
      - Iendyk, Rostislav (Yendyk, Rostyslav; 1906-1974; Anthropologist, belletrist, and publicist), 1953
      - [Ierastov], 1948
      - Ieremiiv, Mykhailo (1889-1975; Journalist and civic leader), 1930-1954
      - Insabato, Enrico (1878-1963; Italian political activist and publicist, expert on Arabian and Ukrainian affairs, and supporter of Ukrainian independence), 1950
      - [Iryclij], 1946
    - J 1930-1950, [Box 2, Folder 18].
      - Jaskiewicz, Jan, 1923
      - Jean, Josaphat Joseph O.S.B.M. (1885-1972; Missionary priest), 1948
      - Jodko, Th., 1938
      - Joyce, F., 1952
    - K 1919-1954, [Box 2, Folder 19].
      - Kalinowski, Ed., 1930
      - Kalynnyk, O., 1954
      - [Kampy, Robert and Viviane], 1953
      - Kedrovskyi, Volodymyr (1890-1970; Journalist military and political activist), 1921-1950
      - Kholodnyi, Petro (1902-; Painter and graphic artist), 1936
      - Khoma, Ivan (1923-; Clergyman and scholar), 1954
      - Khomenko, Ivan (Ukr. Catholic priest and biblical scholar), 1954
      - Körber, Hans, 1951-1954
      - Kornodowicz, Zofia, 1910
      - Kovalskyi, Mykola (1899-1976; Civic and political figure; publicist), 1950
      - Kreura, Fr. B., 1949-1951
      - [Kvynytadze, H.], 1951
      - unidentified, 1938
      - unidentified, 1953
    - L 1919-1950, [Box 2, Folder 20].
      - Labry Roger, n.d.
      - Landin, Beffine, 1947-1950
      - Lanskoi, Mykh., 1921
      - Lanzarini, Andrea ("L'osservatore Romano"), 1942-1950
      - Latvian Legation, 1950
      - Lebed, Mykola (1909-; Revolutionary and Ukrainian nationalist leader), 1953
      - Lévi, Sylvain; (Société Asiatique) (1863-1935), 1935
      - [Lilicuft, Benita], 1946
      - Lithuanian Legation, 1953
      - [Loi, Stanislav], 1922-1928
      - Lototska, Olena (1894-1975; Activist of the women's movement), 1950
      - Lovits, Oskar, 1952
      - Lubomirsky, M., 1919
      - Lukhianenko, Marta, 1954
      - unidentified, 1919
      - unidentified, 1950-1954
      - unidentified, n.d.
      - Livytskyi, Andrii(1879-1954; Jurist and civic and political leader), 1922-1929
      - Livytskyi, Andrii, 1930-1935
      - Lypynskyi, Viacheslav (1882-1931; Historian, political philosopher, and publicist), 1921-1926, [Box 2, Folder 20a].
    - M 1920-1950, [Box 2, Folder 21].
      - Magallon d'Argens, le marquis Xavier de (1866-), 1927
      - Maglakelize, Shalva, 1948-1950
      - Malaniuk, Ievhen (1897-1968; poet and political and community activist), 1947
      - Marczak, Michal, 1929
      - Markó, Mária, 1950
      - Matushevskyi, Iu., 1947
      - Maurogordato, [S.], 1920-1921
      - Mazade, Fernand (1863-1939; French poet, critic, and journalist), 1922-193?
      - Memalek, Mochaverol (Ambassade Impériale de Perse), 1920
      - Meshk, Petro, 1953
      - Milanch, G.T., 1950
      - Montaigle, Comte Thomas de, 1953
      - Montesquieu, J de, 1924-1925
      - Montesquieu, A. de baronne, 1929
      - Montrésor, Adam, 1921-1938
      - [Montupieu, J. de], 1924-1925
      - Morillo, Fr. Jakiw S.J., 1948-1952
      - Mukhyn, Mykhailo (1894-1974; Literary scholar and publicist), 1949
      - Muret, Maurice (1870-1954), 1927
      - Murska, Sofiia, 1936-1937
      - Mylianyk, Fr. Iurii, 1950
      - Myronenko, M., 1951
      - unidentified, 1919
      - unidentified, 1930
      - unidentified, n.d.
    - N 1922-1950, [Box 2, Folder 22].
      - Nagai, M. (Ambassade du Japon), n.d.
      - Nahai, S., 1952-1953
      - Narducci, Colomba, 1950
      - Noulens, Joseph (1864-; Ambassadeur de France), 1931-1933
      - Nuntiatura Apostolica Poloniae, 1922
      - N., V., 1937
    - O 1936-1952, [Box 2, Folder 23].
      - O'Brien, Grace, 1946-1950
      - Oleskiv, Vasyl (1924-; Emigré political leader), 1949-1953
      - Oliinychenko, Panas (1888-?), 1952
      - Orsini, Lelio Nicolo, 1937
      - re: Osetskyi, Oleksander (1873-1937; Senior UNR Army officer), 1936
      - Ostroverkha, Mykhailo (1897-1979; Writer and journalist), 1936
      - unidentified, n.d.
    - P 1918-1953, [Box 3, Folder 24].
      - Paléologue, Count Chapelle, 1950
      - Paléologue-Crivez, Prince Paul Théodore, 1947-1951
      - Pallavicini, Oberto, 1950
      - Panchuk, B., 1949-1951
      - Parsons, Renate and Richard, 1947-1948
      - Patrizi, Giuseppe Fra, 1940-1943
      - Pavlykovska, Iryna (1901-1975; Civic leader), n.d.
      - Pearson, Fred, 1952
      - Péladan, C., n.d.
      - Les Amis de Péladan, 1924-1925
      - Pelenski, Jaroslaw Z., 1953
      - Perebyinis, Tetiana, 1954
      - Perebyinis, Vasyl (1898-1966; Artist), 1935-1950
      - Petrusewicz, Stanislaw, 1952-1953
      - Picoy, ?], 1930-1932
      - Pilsudska, Aleksandra (1882-), 1935
      - Piotrowski, T. Edward Henry de Corvin, 1952
      - Pisniachevskyi, Viktor (1883-1933; Physician, journalist, and civic leader), 1921
      - Pizzi, Franco and Alda, 1946-1954
      - Potocka, Jadwiga, 1940-1948
      - Potocki, Stanislaw, 1918-1926
      - Potocki, Stefan Cedric, 1941-1948
      - Prokopovych, Viacheslav (1881-1942; Political leader, pedagogue, publicist, and historian), 1926-1931
      - Pronopontey, V., 1922
      - Prykhodko, Viktor (1886-1982; Lawyer and civic and cultural figure), 1921-1949
      - Puget-Paléologue, Comte Joseph Borg-Olivier de, 1952-1953
      - unidentified, 1922-1933
      - unidentified, 1932
      - unidentified, 1934
      - Petliura, Symon(1879-1926; Statesman and publicist; supreme commander of the UNR Army and president of the Directory of the Ukrainian National Republic), 1922-1925
    - Q 1921-1932, [Box 3, Folder 25].
      - Quenet, l'Abbé Charles, 1922-1932
    - R 1921-1950, [Box 3, Folder 26].
      - Raghib Raif Bey, n.d.
      - Rapicavoli, Carm., 1931-1936
      - Rekov, Oleksander, 1921-1942
      - Robertiello, Federico, 1950
      - Rochford, Helen, 1950
      - Rocke, Betsy and Cyril, 1943-1953
      - Rudychiv, I. (Petliura Ukrainian Library), 1931-1936
      - Rusov, Iurii, 1895-1961; Biologist), 1939-1954
      - Rusova, Sofiia (1856-1940; Pedagogue, author, and political activist; founding member and first president of the National Council of Women), n.d.
      - unidentified, 1938-1951
      - Ratti, Ambrogio Damiano Achille, 1918-1919, [Box 3, Folder 27].
    - S 1922-1950, [Box 3, Folder 28].
      - Salvini, Luigi (1911-1957; Italian Slavist), 1945
      - Samonek, S., 1923
      - Sani, 1943-1950
      - Sapun, P., 1952
      - Savastano, Galileo, 1943
      - Scibor-Rylski, A., 1952-1953
      - Sculér, Pierre de, 1951-1953
      - Semeniw, Alexander, 1930-1936
      - Serbanesco, D.G.R. (Demeter Gerard Roger), 1954
      - Shakman, M., n.d.
      - Shandruk, Pavlo (Chanedroucq, Paul; 1889-1979; Senior UNR Army officer), 1935
      - Shulhyn, Oleksander (Choulguine, Alexandre; 1889-1960; Political leader, community and cultural activist, historian, and sociologist), 1928
      - Sikorskyi, Polikarp (1875-1953; Metropolitan of the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox church), 1934-1950
      - Silli, P. Antonino O.P., 1950
      - [Skrutenkyi, M.], 1925
      - Smal-Stocki, Roman (1893-1969; Scholar and political figure), 1933
      - Solovii, V., 1950
      - Somssich, Comte (International Refugee Organization (Italy)), 1950
      - Soulier, Edouard, 1927-1928
      - Stakhiv, Volodymyr (1910-1971); Journalist and political activist), 1953
      - Stetsko, Iaroslav (1912-1986; Political leader and ideologue of the Ukrainian nationalist movement), 1950
      - Stewart, John F. (Scottish League for European Freedom), 1954
      - Sushytskyi, Iurii, 1936-1937
      - Svientsitskyi, Ilarion (1876-1956; Philologist, paleographer, museologist, art historian, and bibliographer), 1934
      - unidentified, 1927
      - unidentified, 1950
      - unidentified, 1953
      - unidentified, 1954
      - Sheptytskyi, Andrii (1865-1944; Church, cultural, and civic figure; metropolitan of Halych, archbishop of Lviv, and bishop of Kamianets-Podilskyi), 1918-1942, [Box 3, Folder 29].
      - Szewczuk 1948, 1953-1945, [Box 3, Folder 30].
    - T 1927-1928, 1952-1953, [Box 3, Folder 31].
      - Tabouis, Georges (1867-1958; French general, commissioner of the French Republic to the government of the UNR), 1927-1938
      - Tarnowska, Anna, n.d.
      - Tarnowsky, Michel de, 1937
      - Tisserand, Roger, 1932-1938
      - Tokarzewski, Michal, 1946-1953
      - Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz, Jerzy, 1949-1950
      - Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz, S.S., 1923-1938
      - Torosiewicz, Stanislaw, 1925
      - Trembitskyi, V., 1952-1953
      - Tyszkiewicz, Michel (Tyshkevych, Mykhailo; 1857-1930; Diplomat, publicist, artist, and patron of Ukrainian culture), 1913-1926
        - Tyszkiewicz, Michel 1913-1926, [Box 3, Folder 32].
        - Tyszkiewicz, Michel 1918-1930, [Box 3, Folder 33].
    - U 1928, [Box 3, Folder 34].
      - Ukrainian Publishers Ltd. (1949-), 1951-1954
      - Ukrainian Youth Association (1946-), 1949-1954
      - Union des Anciens Combattants de l'Armée de la République Democratique Ukrainienne en France, 1928
      - [Urquhart, H.], n.d.
    - V-W 1919-1952, [Box 4, Folder 35].